Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series I. Outgoing Correspondence from Vladimir Nabokov 1947-1975
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 17, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Writing from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, VN is amazed to hear from Gallimard that they have signed a contract with Kahane to do the translation of Lolita. He cannot believe that Ergaz should not have attended to VN's refusal to consider Kahane, cites a letter from E. signalling her acceptance of such a refusal, and concludes that the contract with Kahane exists only in the imagination of Michel Mohrt.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, July 12, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Not addressed, in French, detailing further woes involving Girodias, specifically his non-response to overtures by British publishing firms Jonathan Cape and Bodley Head (where Graham Greene is now consulting director), and extravagant demands that seem to make the American publication of Lolita by a first-class publishing house unlikely. Mention of Bodley Head's plans to publish Lolita in a limited edition in order to test the censorship waters.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, September 7, 1957 (1), with enclosed copy of TL to Vladimir Nabokov from Mr. M. Girodias, September 5, 1957 (2). (Box 1, Folder 46)
    (1) Writing from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, VN is sorry that the deal with Doubleday if off since they were the most likely to make the book a brilliant American success, but mentions that he is putting G. in touch with two other publishers, McDowell Obolensky, and Putnam. Wants to know what he is to tell Bodley Head, and expresses unhappiness about the payment of royalties. Pencil note (Véra?): "copy for Mme. Ergaz." (2) Writing from The Olympia Press, Girodias mentions that he has heard from Putnam, but feels that any negotiation with them will be fruitless, as all such negotiations have been and will continue to be until VN modifies his demands. G. confirms that he will take no decision without VN's written consent. Dated earlier than (1) but probably received after (1) written or sent. Pencil note (Véra): "for Mme. Ergaz".
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, September 10, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, discussing Girodias' demands with regard to the American publication of Lolita and the dispute over royalties, and explaining that it will be easy for VN to look at the French translation of Lolita before Cornell classes begin on September 22. Thanks Ergaz for the nice things she has said about Pnin.
  - TL to Messrs. Mahlström & Widstrand, A.B. from Vladimir Nabokov, September 13, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Not addressed, in English, noting with dismay that the text of Lolita has been abridged, "crippled and stripped", and "not" mentioning "incredible mistranslations, and requesting immediate action on the part of the publishers. Pencil note: "copie." Probably accompanied 1-46.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Véra Nabokov, September 15, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Not addressed, in French. Véra writes that her husband would like Ergaz to take a look at the letter he has sent to the Swedish publishers W. and W., and that he hopes they will comply, but asks for Ergaz's advice if they do not. Exclaims, "Pauvre LOLITA!"
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, September 18, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing vexation, irritation, indignation, and a sense of being insulted by Girodias' obnoxious request that VN lower his royalty demands. VN asks that Ergaz write to ascertain G.'s intentions, because he himself will be unable to remain polite.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, October 5, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Written on Cornell letterhead from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, declaring the agreement between VN and Olympia "null and void". Included in Vladimir Nabokov, Selected Letters 1940-1977, p. 228.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, October 5, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Written on Cornell letterhead from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, declaring the agreement between VN and Olympia "null and void". Colored pencil annotation: "copie". Possibly enclosed with 1-50.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 5, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, asking Ergaz to "see" (and probably enclosing a copy of) what he has found himself forced to write to Girodias (1-48 or 1-49).
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 15, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, expressing great disappointment not only with the conduct of Girodias, who VN claims has not only been lax in paying the royalties due him, but has also acted in bad faith since the beginning of their relationship (he cites a number of examples, including G.'s about-face on the subject of British publication, as well as his negotiations with American publishing houses), but also with Ergaz, who has reproached VN for his indignation and failed to answer his concerns regarding the translation of Lolita. Suggests that Ergaz has received a twisted version of events from Girodias, and attempts to put her straight. Some underlining in pencil.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, November 7, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, on the eve of a trip to New York, concerning the French translation of Lolita, especially Kahane's refusal to send VN his translation in parts as it is composed, and referencing Girodias' threats to publish Lolita in the US under the imprint of Olympia Press, which VN does not take very seriously. Wonders at G.'s claimed incomprehension of the reasons for VN's attempt to terminate their contract. Agrees to conditional advances from Gallimard for Conclusive Evidence and Pnin. Pencil annotation.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, November 21, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    From Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, VN writes that the "reasons for my behavior have been fully explained to my agent" and that G. may apply to her for information. Outlines the incomprehensibility of G.'s behavior. Is sorry the situation has developed as it has, but refuses the blame.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, November 21, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Carbon of 1-53.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, November 21, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, thanking Ergaz for various letters and contracts that he has signed and is returning, save for the Gallimard contract, to which he objects. Mentions threat by G. to publish a limited edition of Lolita in the US, and hopes Ergaz has explained to G. that it will be easy for VN to have such an edition seized, and that VN will not hesitate to do so. Is interested in a legal opinion on his rupture with Olympia. Despairs of the Lolita translation. In a postscript referring to a new demand of G.'s, claims that he sees no reason to grant G. anything at all. Pencil annotation, possibly by the agent.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, December 11, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, noting that he has received a letter from Kahane to the effect that the first volume of Lolita will appear soon, asserting that the problems between he and Girodias are hardly confined to the question of Lolita's relative cost in France and the US, and refusing the Gallimard contract for Lolita unless the latter excludes the film rights.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, December 23, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, asking Ergaz to refuse all attempt at payment by Girodias, and calling a G.'s check of 178 francs an attempt to "get a rise out of me". Finds the Kahane translation very good, if in need of some minor corrections. Wonders what Ergaz's lawyer friend advises re: his (non)termination of contract with Olympia. Some pencil markings.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, December 30, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, going through the points of his disagreement with Girodias (apparently in response to a request by Ergaz), explaining that at one point VN contemplated initiating legal action against Olympia. Asserts that the contract is American, and that the American courts are competent. Pencil underlining, probably VN's.
  - TL to Mr. M. Girodias from Vladimir Nabokov, January 3, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, in dismay over the news that Walter Minton (Putnam) has discussed an agreement based on a 50/50 division of royalties. VN would rather not publish at all in the US under such conditions. Pencil note (probably Véra's): "copie (pour votre dossiers)."
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 18, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, complaining of Ergaz's delay in letting him know of her lawyer friend's advice re: the contract with Olympia, her silence on the subject of the judgment that overturned the ban on Lolita and other Olympia Press Books (it was Girodias who telegraphed him the news), and explaining the necessity for a new contract with G. A vague threat of initiating court proceedings against G. According to postscript, letter delayed in posting by snow storm.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 15, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, noting that Putnam has sent a contract to Girodias according the latter a 7.5% royalty, something to which VN, though firmly opposed, has acceded on Putnam's advice, and asking after the publication status of various works ( Conclusive Evidence, Pnin, and Invitation). Pencil annotations.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, March 16, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, offering a 5% commission on the Putnam contract to Ergaz.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, September 16, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, wondering why he was not informed, by either Girodias or Ergaz, of the new ban on Lolita, and wanting more information on the British police's view of Lolita as a borderline case. Hints at an advantageous new offer for Lolita by an unnamed British firm and notes that he has received, via Ergaz, a check for the Lolita royalties from Girodias.
  - 5 Telegrams to D. Clairouin from Vladimir Nabokov, 1948-1958. (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Written from Cambridge (1) and Ithaca (4) regarding publication and translation of Lolita and Invitation to a Beheading.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 10, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in French, responding to letter from Ergaz about her commission, expressing confusion over her statement that half her commission is due from the editor, and asking why Girodias owes her money unless it is for services rendered? Some discussion of VN's short prose works and their publication history. Markings in pen.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 3, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, asking that he and Ergaz assess the status of the numerous ongoing contract negotiations, requiring from E. a list of the titles she has sold or is trying to sell and to whom, and explaining that VN would like to negotiate his contracts himself. Thanks E. for "amusing" clippings.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 6, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, asking that Ergaz call off a deal with Steimatzki (Israeli publisher) as VN has heard they do not always live up to their obligation. Pencil note (probably Véra's) explaining what came immediately of the letter.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 12, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, on various contract matters, including VN's intention to negotiate the Rowohlt contract directly with Hamburg, and continued Steimatzki mess.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 19, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Written from Goldwin Smith Hall, Ithaca NY, in English, detailing VN's various grievances re: the Steimatzki matter, including suspicions that Ergaz is either acting carelessly or in cahoots with Girodias (as indicated by the fact that G. has seen at least one of VN's letters to Ergaz), and continued irritation with Girodias. Refuses to discuss any publication matters with Ergaz until the "Steimatzki matter has been taken care of to my satisfaction."
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, March 10, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Written c/o Putnam's Sons, 210 Madison Avenue, New York 16, in English, complaining about the "long introduction [to the Olympia Press Traveller's Companion edition of Lolita]. Discussion of which short stories may be published, and various translation issues. VN seems to have warmed to Eric Kahane, as the latter is proposed as possible translator for all of the texts mentioned in this letter.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 18, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Written from Sedona AZ, in English, dealing with various issues under headings (CHAMBRE OBSCURE, GIRODIAS etc.). Is delighted with Gallimard's presentation of Lolita, rather irritably asks whether Frs. 20.000 is the customary honorarium for a short story by "authors in my category," asserts that the afterword to Lolita is famous and ought to be paid for, and discusses a possible Portuguese translation of Lolita.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, June 17, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Written from Sedona AZ, in English, with small portion in French, concerning translation and contractual matters. Documents VN's disillusionment with Ergaz and her underhanded strategies, as he continues to assert his intention of conducting all negotiations with publishers directly, reminding Ergaz that she has no stake in negotiations even with publishers whom she had introduced to VN.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, June 18, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Written from Sedona AZ, in English, dealing with the "pirated" French re-publication of Laughter in the Dark by Grasset, especially Ergaz's lapsed rights in regard to that text and her (to VN) incredible assertion that she knew nothing of Grasset's plans until the book appeared.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, June 23, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Written from Sedona AZ, in English, dealing once more with the Grasset pirated edition of Laughter, expressing VN's wish to prosecute this "monstrous" act, and refusing all compromise with Grasset.
  - TLS to Mademoiselle Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, July 1, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Written from Sedona AZ, in English, concerning payment by Steimatzki, with whom VN insists he has not signed a contract. Asserts that any English-language edition of Lolita published in Israel is a "separate issue of the Olympia edition", and therefore he will accept Steimatzki's check as a payment from Olympia.
  - TLS to Monsieur Maurice Nadeau from Vladimir Nabokov, July 11, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Probably written from Arizona, in French, concerning the botched translation of the acrostic that ends Vane Sisters. Outlines course of action VN wishes Nadeau to follow in this matter, and includes demand for payment for Les Lettres Nouvelles's unauthorized 1957 reproduction of a Lolita fragment.
  - TLS to Mademoiselle Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, September 8, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Written from Hotel Park Cresecent, 87th and Riverside Drive, New York, in English, concerning the Grasset matter, especially a new contract for Laughter in the Dark. The VNs' are to set sail for Europe (Switzerland, England, France) on September 25.
  - TLS to Mademoiselle Marie Schébéko from Véra Nabokov, September 25, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Not addressed, but probably written in New York, in English, citing a lawyer's opinion regarding Olympia's rights in Lolita. VN wishes attention drawn to the last paragraph of the opinion, which states that negotiations and contracts for foreign language publication are no concern of Olympia's. Notes existence of gaudy and pirated Turkish edition of Lolita, and wonders what can be done about it. Some markings in pen.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 5, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Written from Hôtel Astoria, Menton, in French, concerning a legal dispute between Girodias and Mme. Hummel over the rights to foreign language publications of Lolita that would affect payments by Erhaz to Olympia. Denies that Olympia has the right to publish a paperback edition of Lolita, and reiterates that he is distinctly opposed to Ergaz showing VN's contracts to Olympia. Some pencil markings.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 27, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Written from 57 Promenade des Anglais, Nice, in French, demanding that Ergaz cease legal proceedings against Girodias as VN had asked in an earlier telegram. Cannot see why things cannot be resolved without lawyers ("Simple comme bonjour"). Believes himself to be in the right, but finds that it will cost too much (financially and in terms of his work) to achieve the ideal result (i.e. a complete break with Olympia). Demands clarification of Ergaz's reference to possible unknown "pocketbook" contracts. Threatens to resume proceedings if Olympia does not submit its accounts.
  - TL to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 27, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Written from Nice, in French, copy of 2-16.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, February 9, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Written from 57 Promenade des Anglais, Nice, in French, regretting that it is proving so difficult to resolve matters, but asking Ergaz to note that the wishes of Girodias are of no concern to VN and that proceedings be started to force Olympia to render account. Underlining in pen.
  - TLS to the Bureau Littéraire D. Clairouin from Vladimir Nabokov, March 9, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Written from 57 Promenade des Anglais, Nice, in French, asking his agents to retain all money owing Olympia while Olympia continues to withold money owing VN. Asks the agents to consider this letter a formal declaration.
  - TLS to ? from Vladimir Nabokov, March 18, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Written from 57 Promenade des Anglais, Nice, in French, attesting that the original edition of his work entitled Lolita is the one published in English by Olympia Press.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, November 15, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, requesting the amount of the sum due Olympia.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, November 20, 1961. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, concerning the amount owing Olympia from sales of the Swedish and Israeli pocketbook editions of Lolita. Now that these editions are no longer part of the litigation against Olympia, VN sees no reason not to pay them. Note in pen explaining enclosed check.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 16, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, regarding Chrestien's translation of Pnin, which VN has begun to correct. Is exhausted after completing Pale Fire, and while VN believes it is important to ameliorate the translation, is appalled by the amount of effort required by each French translation of his novels ("un peu de cauchmar").
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, January 27, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, regarding Chrestien's translation of Pnin, which VN has now completed, though with great difficulty. Would love to meet C., but sees no point in his coming to Montreux to meet the Nabokovs, as VN cannot possibly spare the time he deserves, while Chrestien ought to occupy himself with corrections. Thinks Pale Fire will prove more difficult to translate than Pnin or even Lolita, and will need to see a sample of the translator's work before deciding. Unflattering assessment of Faulkner's style.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, April 28, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Not addressed, in French, regarding Chrestien's negligence, which VN finds exasperating. Is leaving for America on the Queen Elizabeth, and has just received the first American edition of Pale Fire. Note in pencil, probably the agent's.
  - TL to Centre National du Cinema à Paris from Vladimir Nabokov, June 15, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in French, confirming that the signature on the contract ceding the movie rights to Laughter in the Dark is that of Irving Lazar.
  - TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Véra Nabokov, May 1, 1963 (1), with appended TLS to Madame Marie Schébéko from Vladimir Nabokov, May 2, 1963 (2). (Box 2, Folder 27)
    (1) Not addressed, in French, asking that a short story be placed with L'Arc, which intends to devote an issue to "the writer VN." (2) Not addressed, in French, regarding contract with Mondadori for two pocket editions of Lolita.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, May 6, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Written from Palace Hôtel, Montreux, in English, expressing satisfaction with a sample of Girard's translation of Pale Fire, and thanking Ergaz and Mohrt for the trouble they have taken in this matter. With instructions should Girard agree to undertake the translation (as VN hopes he will). Postscript suggesting that VN be compensated for the checking and revising he is forced to do.
  - TL to Monsieur Raymond Girard from Vladimir Nabokov, October 4, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Not addressed, in French, detailing the pleasure with which he has read Girard's translation of Pale Fire, particularly with regard to the brilliance of Girard's "trouvailles". Explains, in response to a question of Girard's, what is meant by Odin's Hall, and by the phrase "pale fire."
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 4, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) for the Foreword of Pale Fire, translated by Raymond Girard. Page 1.
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 4, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) for the Foreword of Pale Fire, translated by Raymond Girard. Page 2.
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 4, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) for the Foreword of Pale Fire, translated by Raymond Girard. Page 3.
  - Typed corrections sent to Raymond Girard by Vladimir Nabokov, October 4, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Typescript of corrections (in French) for the Foreword of Pale Fire, translated by Raymond Girard. Page 4. Pencil annotations.
  - TLS to Madame D. Ergaz from Vladimir Nabokov, October 19, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 34)